A Guide to the Records of Central State Hospital, 1874-1961
Library of Virginia
- Series II. Commitment Papers, 1874-1906. (Box 1-107.)
  - 1905.
    - B. (Box 95, Folder 4)
    - B. (Box 95, Folder 5)
    - B. (Box 95, Folder 6)
    - B. (Box 95, Folder 7)
    - B. (Box 95, Folder 8)
    - B. (Box 95, Folder 9)
    - C. (Box 96, Folder 1)
    - C. (Box 96, Folder 2)
    - C. (Box 96, Folder 3)
    - C. (Box 96, Folder 4)
    - C. (Box 96, Folder 5)
    - C. (Box 96, Folder 6)
    - D. (Box 96, Folder 7)
    - D. (Box 96, Folder 8)
    - E. (Box 96, Folder 9)
    - E. (Box 96, Folder 10)
    - F. (Box 96, Folder 11)
    - F. (Box 96, Folder 12)
    - G. (Box 97, Folder 1)
    - G. (Box 97, Folder 2)
    - G. (Box 97, Folder 3)
    - G. (Box 97, Folder 4)
    - H. (Box 97, Folder 5)
    - H. (Box 97, Folder 6)
    - H. (Box 97, Folder 7)
    - H. (Box 97, Folder 8)
    - H. (Box 97, Folder 9)
    - H. (Box 97, Folder 10)
    - J. (Box 98, Folder 1)
    - J. (Box 98, Folder 2)
    - J. (Box 98, Folder 3)
    - J. (Box 98, Folder 4)
    - J. (Box 98, Folder 5)
    - J. (Box 98, Folder 6)
    - K. (Box 98, Folder 7)
    - L. (Box 98, Folder 8)
    - L. (Box 98, Folder 9)
    - M. (Box 98, Folder 10)
    - M. (Box 98, Folder 11)
    - M. (Box 99, Folder 1)
    - M. (Box 99, Folder 2)
    - Mc. (Box 99, Folder 3)
    - N. (Box 99, Folder 4)
    - N. (Box 99, Folder 5)
    - P. (Box 99, Folder 6)
    - P. (Box 99, Folder 7)
    - R. (Box 99, Folder 8)
    - S. (Box 99, Folder 9)
    - S. (Box 99, Folder 10)
    - S. (Box 99, Folder 11)
    - S. (Box 99, Folder 12)
    - S. (Box 100, Folder 1)
    - S. (Box 100, Folder 2)
    - T. (Box 100, Folder 3)
    - T. (Box 100, Folder 4)
    - T. (Box 100, Folder 5)
    - U-V. (Box 100, Folder 6)
    - W. (Box 100, Folder 7)
    - W. (Box 100, Folder 8)
    - W. (Box 100, Folder 9)
    - W. (Box 100, Folder 10)
    - W. (Box 100, Folder 11)
    - W. (Box 100, Folder 12)
    - W. (Box 101, Folder 1)
    - W. (Box 101, Folder 2)
    - Y. (Box 101, Folder 3)
  - 1906.
    - A. (Box 101, Folder 4)
    - B. (Box 101, Folder 5)
    - B. (Box 101, Folder 6)
    - B. (Box 101, Folder 7)
    - B. (Box 101, Folder 8)
    - B. (Box 101, Folder 9)
    - B. (Box 101, Folder 10)
    - C. (Box 101, Folder 11)
    - C. (Box 102, Folder 1)
    - C. (Box 102, Folder 2)
    - C. (Box 102, Folder 3)
    - C. (Box 102, Folder 4)
    - C. (Box 102, Folder 5)
    - D. (Box 102, Folder 6)
    - D. (Box 102, Folder 7)
    - E. (Box 102, Folder 8)
    - F. (Box 102, Folder 9)
    - F. (Box 102, Folder 10)
    - G. (Box 102, Folder 11)
    - G. (Box 102, Folder 12)
    - G. (Box 103, Folder 1)
    - H. (Box 103, Folder 2)
    - H. (Box 103, Folder 3)
    - H. (Box 103, Folder 4)
    - H. (Box 103, Folder 5)
    - H. (Box 103, Folder 6)
    - I. (Box 103, Folder 7)
    - J. (Box 103, Folder 8)
    - J. (Box 103, Folder 9)
    - J. (Box 103, Folder 10)
    - J. (Box 103, Folder 11)
    - J. (Box 103, Folder 12)
    - K. (Box 103, Folder 13)
    - K. (Box 104, Folder 1)
    - L. (Box 104, Folder 2)
    - L. (Box 104, Folder 3)
    - M. (Box 104, Folder 4)
    - M. (Box 104, Folder 5)
    - M. (Box 104, Folder 6)
    - Mc. (Box 104, Folder 7)
    - N. (Box 104, Folder 8)
    - P. (Box 104, Folder 9)
    - P. (Box 104, Folder 10)
    - P. (Box 104, Folder 11)
    - P. (Box 104, Folder 12)
    - R. (Box 105, Folder 1)
    - R. (Box 105, Folder 2)
    - R. (Box 105, Folder 3)
    - R. (Box 105, Folder 4)
    - S. (Box 105, Folder 5)
    - S. (Box 105, Folder 6)
    - S. (Box 105, Folder 7)
    - S. (Box 105, Folder 8)
    - T. (Box 105, Folder 9)
    - T. (Box 105, Folder 10)
    - T. (Box 105, Folder 11)
    - T. (Box 106, Folder 1)
    - W. (Box 106, Folder 2)
    - W. (Box 106, Folder 3)
    - W. (Box 106, Folder 4)
    - W. (Box 106, Folder 5)
    - W. (Box 106, Folder 6)
    - W. (Box 106, Folder 7)
    - W. (Box 106, Folder 8)
  - Rejected Applicants.
    - 1905 B-G. (Box 106, Folder 9)
    - 1905 H-P. (Box 106, Folder 10)
    - 1905 S-W. (Box 106, Folder 11)
    - 1906 B-D. (Box 107, Folder 1)
    - 1906 F-M. (Box 107, Folder 2)
    - 1906 S-W. (Box 107, Folder 3)
    - 1907 B-G. (Box 107, Folder 4)
    - 1907 H-R. (Box 107, Folder 5)
    - 1907 T. (Box 107, Folder 6)
- Series III. Construction Records, 1904-1938. (Box 108.)
  Contains a variety of construction-related documents including building appraisals, bids, as well as contracts and specifications for structures and systems located on the Central State Hospital campus.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of document.
  - Building Appraisals, 1926. (Box 108, Folder 1)
  - Construction Bids, 1904. (Box 108, Folder 2)
  - Construction Costs, 1928-1932. (Box 108, Folder 3)
  - Contracts/Specifications: Building for Chronic Female Patients, 1914. (Box 108, Folder 4)
  - Contracts/Specifications: Building for Chronic Female Patients, 1914. (Box 108, Folder 5)
  - Contracts/Specifications: Building for Female Patients, 1904. (Box 108, Folder 6)
  - Contracts/Specifications: Chapel, 1904-1905. (Box 108, Folder 7)
  - Contracts/Specifications: Cottages for Consumptives, 1904. (Box 108, Folder 8)
  - Contracts/Specifications: Criminal Building, Southeast Wing, 1916. (Box 108, Folder 9)
  - Contracts/Specifications: Criminal Building, Wing, 1912. (Box 108, Folder 10)
  - Contracts/Specifications: Female Criminal Building, 1928. (Box 108, Folder 11)
  - Contracts/Specifications: Fire Escape, Male Psychopathic Building, 1928. (Box 108, Folder 12)
  - Contracts/Specifications: Fire System, 1928. (Box 108, Folder 13)
  - Contracts/Specifications: Heating and Hot Water System, 1912; 1938. (Box 108, Folder 14)
  - Contracts/Specifications: Hospital Building, 1928. (Box 108, Folder 15)
  - Contracts/Specifications: Industrial Shop, 1904-1905. (Box 108, Folder 16)
  - Contracts/Specifications: Kitchen Floor, 1913. (Box 108, Folder 17)
  - Contracts/Specifications: Male Attendant's Building, 1905. (Box 108, Folder 18)
  - Contracts/Specifications: Pavilion for Female Tubercular Patients, 1912. (Box 108, Folder 19)
  - Contracts/Specifications: Psychopathic Building for Male Patients, 1913. (Box 108, Folder 20)
  - Contracts/Specifications: Sewage Disposal System, 1912. (Box 108, Folder 21)
  - Contracts/Specifications: Ward Building, 1932. (Box 108, Folder 22)
  - Contracts/Specifications: Water Plant, 1915. (Box 108, Folder 23)
- Series IV. Deeds and Leases, 1882-1942. (Box 109.)
  Contains deeds and land leases for property owned and used by Central State Hospital. Much of the deeded land was bought from private land owners, while other land was deeded by railroad companies, the City of Petersburg, Virginia, and the United States of America. The land leases were made between private land owners and the hospital for the temporary use of certain parcels of property.
  Arranged alphabetically by document type (deed or lease), and then alphabetically by the other party's last name.
  - Deed: Atlantic Coast Line Railroad Co. / Virginia Railway and Power Co. (Sewer Line), 1913. (Box 109, Folder 1)
  - Deed: Bowles, Clifton A. (Crawford House), 1936-1940. (Box 109, Folder 2)
  - Deed: Burns and Campbell (Estate of Joseph Burns), 1934. (Box 109, Folder 3)
  - Deed: Byrd, Cornelia, 1928. (Box 109, Folder 4)
  - Deed: Gerecke Property, 1925. (Box 109, Folder 5)
  - Deed: Jackson/Griffin Property (Blythefield), 1903-1904. (Box 109, Folder 6)
  - Deed: Lassiter, Charles T. and Wife, 1898-1920. (Box 109, Folder 7)
  - Deed: Lassiter, Charles T. and Wife, 1923-1942. (Box 109, Folder 8)
  - Deeds: Miscellaneous Documents, 1926-1942. (Box 109, Folder 9)
  - Deed: Norfolk and Western Railway Co., 1912. (Box 109, Folder 10)
  - Deed: Petersburg, City of (Mayfield Farm), 1882. (Box 109, Folder 11)
  - Deed: Petersburg, City of (Quarry Tract), 1925. (Box 109, Folder 12)
  - Deed: Roper Realty Corporation, 1925. (Box 109, Folder 13)
  - Deed: United States of America (Petersburg National Military Park), 1928. (Box 109, Folder 14)
  - Deed: Virginia Railway and Power Co. (Sewer Line), 1912. (Box 109, Folder 15)
  - Deed: Zimmer/Mitchell Property, 1886-1912. (Box 109, Folder 16)
  - Land Lease: Boone, Mrs. E.H., 1928-1931. (Box 109, Folder 17)
  - Land Lease: Parker, Mrs. Kitty G., 1926-1931. (Box 109, Folder 18)
- Series V. Furlough Agreements and Bonds, 1903-1911. (Box 110.)
  Contains groupings of furlough agreements for patients who were allowed to leave Central State Hospital, either permanently or temporarily. The agreements were usually signed by a friend or family member who promised to "exercise proper care, protection and restraint" over the patient while he or she was away from the hospital. In some cases, the family was required to offer bond in exchange for the patient's release.
  - 1903-1904. (Box 110, Folder 1)
  - 1904-1905. (Box 110, Folder 2)
  - 1905-1906. (Box 110, Folder 3)
  - 1906-1907. (Box 110, Folder 4)
  - 1909-1910. (Box 110, Folder 5)
  - 1910-1911. (Box 110, Folder 6)
- Series VI. Insurance Records, 1924-1958. (Box 110., Box 1., Map-case 9 Drawer: 1.)
  Contains aerial site plans of the Central State Hospital and Petersburg State Colony complexes, as well as a variety of insurance-related documents such as correspondence, building valuations, and fire and automobile insurance policies.
  Arranged chronologically within in two groups: "Aerial Site Plans" and "Insurance Documents."
  - Aerial Site Plans.
    - Central State Hospital, 1931. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Central State Hospital, 1938. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Central State Hospital and Petersburg State Colony, 1953. (Map-case 9 Drawer: 1)
    - Central State Hospital, 1958. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Central State Hospital, 1958. (Map-case 9 Drawer: 1)
    - Petersburg State Colony, 1951; 1958. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Insurance Documents.
    - 1924-1929. (Box 110, Folder 7)
    - 1930-1937. (Box 110, Folder 8)
    - 1938. (Box 110, Folder 9)
    - 1939. (Box 110, Folder 10)
    - 1941-1949. (Box 110, Folder 11)
    - Undated. (Box 110, Folder 12)
- Series VII. Minutes of the General Board of Directors, 1920-1936. (Box 111.)
  Contains minutes of the General Board of Directors of the State Hospitals and State Colony of Virginia (later known as the State Colony for Epileptics and Feebleminded). The meetings were held on a quarterly basis, with the location rotating between the hospitals. Representatives from each state hospital/colony attended the meetings and were responsible for reporting on the state of their respective institutions. Topics include position apppointments, legislative budget appropriations, patient care and costs, resolutions, and other issues of broad, statewide significance. The reports from each institution's Special Board can be found in Series VIII.
  - 1920. (Box 111, Folder 1)
  - 1921. (Box 111, Folder 2)
  - 1922. (Box 111, Folder 3)
  - 1923. (Box 111, Folder 4)
  - 1924. (Box 111, Folder 5)
  - 1925. (Box 111, Folder 6)
  - 1926. (Box 111, Folder 7)
  - 1927. (Box 111, Folder 8)
  - 1928. (Box 111, Folder 9)
  - 1929. (Box 111, Folder 10)
  - 1930-1931. (Box 111, Folder 11)
  - 1932. (Box 111, Folder 12)
  - 1933. (Box 111, Folder 13)
  - 1934. (Box 111, Folder 14)
  - 1935. (Box 111, Folder 15)
  - 1936. (Box 111, Folder 16)
  - 1936. (Box 111, Folder 17)
- Series VIII. Reports of the Special Boards, 1920-1936. (Box 112-113.)
  Contains quarterly reports of the Special Boards of each of Virginia's mental health institutions as presented at the meetings of the General Board of Directors of State Hospitals and Colony. The institutions represented here are Eastern State Hospital, Southwestern State Hospital, Virginia State Epileptic Colony, and Western State Hospital. The reports given by the representatives of Central State Hospital are not included in this series. The reports contain information on finances, patient population and movements, and a variety of internal operations and items of note. The minutes of the meetings during which these reports were presented can be found in Series VII.
  Arranged chronologically, and then alphabetically by institution within.
  - 1920 October. (Box 112, Folder 1)
  - 1921 January. (Box 112, Folder 2)
  - 1921 April. (Box 112, Folder 3)
  - 1921 July. (Box 112, Folder 4)
  - 1921 October. (Box 112, Folder 5)
  - 1922 January. (Box 112, Folder 6)
  - 1922 April. (Box 112, Folder 7)
  - 1922 July. (Box 112, Folder 8)
  - 1922 October. (Box 112, Folder 9)
  - 1923 January. (Box 112, Folder 10)
  - 1923 March/April. (Box 112, Folder 11)
  - 1923 June/July. (Box 112, Folder 12)
  - 1923 September/October. (Box 112, Folder 13)
  - 1923 December. (Box 112, Folder 14)
  - 1924 March. (Box 112, Folder 15)
  - 1924 June. (Box 112, Folder 16)
  - 1924 September. (Box 112, Folder 17)
  - 1924 December. (Box 112, Folder 18)
  - 1925 June. (Box 112, Folder 19)
  - 1931 June. (Box 112, Folder 20)
  - 1931 September. (Box 112, Folder 21)
  - 1931 December. (Box 112, Folder 22)
  - 1932 March. (Box 113, Folder 1)
  - 1932 June. (Box 113, Folder 2)
  - 1932 September. (Box 113, Folder 3)
  - 1932 December. (Box 113, Folder 4)
  - 1933 March. (Box 113, Folder 5)
  - 1933 September. (Box 113, Folder 6)
  - 1933 September. (Box 113, Folder 7)
  - 1933 December. (Box 113, Folder 8)
  - 1934 March. (Box 113, Folder 9)
  - 1934 June. (Box 113, Folder 10)
  - 1934 September. (Box 113, Folder 11)
  - 1934 December. (Box 113, Folder 12)
  - 1935 March. (Box 113, Folder 13)
  - 1935 June. (Box 113, Folder 14)
  - 1935 September. (Box 113, Folder 15)
  - 1935 December. (Box 113, Folder 16)
  - 1936 March. (Box 113, Folder 17)
  - 1936 June. (Box 113, Folder 18)
  - 1936 September. (Box 113, Folder 19)